{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Charles Ogle supported this man’s candidacy with the Gold Spoon Oration, though his detractors called him “granny.” A newspaper editorial critical of this man inspired his supporters’ “log cabin and hard cider” campaign. His 1811 victory over a group of Shawnee Indians led to his party’s adoption of the slogan “Tippecanoe and Tyler Too”. For ten points, what Whig defeated Martin van Buren in the 1840 election but died of pneumonia a month after his inauguration?",
      "answer": "William Henry Harrison"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the Asuka period in Japan, taxes were levied on this material and cotton. With gold and grain, it served as a currency during the Han Dynasty. A pathway associated with it was originally mapped by Zhang Qian [Jang-Chyen], and, through smuggling, Justinian’s Byzantine Empire acquired the means for this good’s production: mulberry seeds and the eggs of a certain worm. For ten points, name this fabric whose namesake “road” was a trade network linking China to Europe.",
      "answer": "silk"
    },
    {
      "question": "Michael Fay’s treatment at the hands of this nation’s government caused outrage in the mid-1990s. This nation abolished trial by jury in the 1970s, and it hosts the annual Shangri-La Dialogue for world security. The People’s Action Party of this nation frequently sued opponents under the leadership of its recently deceased first President, Lee Kuan Yew. This smallest member of the Four Asian Tigers is notorious for its ban on chewing gum. For ten points, name this island-state on the tip of the Malay Peninsula.",
      "answer": "Singapore"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization used a code called PURPLE to conceal diplomatic messages. This organization built a fortress at Rabaul and was the target of the Great Turkey Shoot. This military force defeated Force Z, consisting of the Prince of Wales and the Repulse, which had been sent to reinforce Malaya. Its forces were concentrated in the Combined Fleet, which suffered the loss of four aircraft carriers at the Battle of Midway. For ten points, name this military force that fought America in the Pacific Ocean during World War II.",
      "answer": [
        "Imperial Japanese Navy",
        "IJN",
        "Combined Fleet until mentioned",
        "descriptive answers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Kelcy Warren serves as the CEO sponsoring this project, which was prohibited from utilizing space under Lake Oahe by the Army Corps of Engineers in December 2016. Shailene Woodley was arrested while protesting this project, which Energy Transfer Partners intends to run to Illinois from the Bakken fields. For ten points, name this pipeline that, controversially, is to run through the Standing Rock Indian Reservation.",
      "answer": [
        "Dakota Access Pipeline or DAPL",
        "Bakken Pipeline before Bakken is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Negroli family, based in Milan, was a key producer of these objects. These objects were manufactured in Greenwich for English monarchs. Decorated versions of these objects were worn at tilts, and Japanese objects of this type were made from overlapping leather scales. These objects included the hauberk and gauntlets, and Roman legionaries wore types of these made from mail or plates. For ten points, name these protective outfits that were used in jousting and medieval warfare.",
      "answer": [
        "suits of armor",
        "any specific piece of armor, such as hauberks",
        "gauntlets before they are mentioned, helmets, etc."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler executed Helvidius Priscus for defending the Senate’s right to manage state finances. This ruler’s bid for power was supported by Mucianus, the governor of Syria. This ruler worked with Agricola in the pacification of Britain, and he became the patron of historian Josephus, who he met while suppressing the Great Jewish Revolt. Shortly after the death of Nero, this man succeeded Vitellius to end the Year of the Four Emperors. For ten points, name this father of Titus and founder of the Flavian dynasty.",
      "answer": "Vespasian or Titus Flavius Vespasianus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Charles Weir invented a device that uses this mineral to compress materials to extremely high pressures. This mineral is the ideal crystal for ATR infrared spectroscopy. These minerals are often found in kimberlite pipes, which are named for a town in South Africa. For ten points, name this allotrope of carbon, a mineral created under extremely high temperatures and pressure that defines the value of 10 on Mohs’ scale of hardness.",
      "answer": "diamonds"
    },
    {
      "question": "One work in this genre describes three generations of tribesmen led by Seitek, Semetei, and Manas. The demon Adamastor is battled by a group of sailors in one of these pieces of literature that tells of Vasco de Gama’s voyage to India. Elias Lonrot compiled one of these works of literature from oral tradition, including the story of the creation of the Sampo. The Lusiads and the Kalevala are examples of, for ten points, what type of literature with a grand scope, such as the Odyssey?",
      "answer": [
        "epic poems",
        "national epics"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was placed under house arrest after an outpouring of grief on Tomb-Sweeping Day; that came during a period of turmoil in which this man’s son was thrown out of a fourth-story window. This man, who succeeded the proponent of the “Two Whatevers,” Hua Guofeng [hwa gwo-fun], established Special Economic Zones as part of a philosophy that he summarized as “It doesn’t matter whether a cat is white or black, as long as it catches mice.” For ten points, name this “paramount leader” of China from 1978 to 1992 who began the country’s market reforms.",
      "answer": "Deng Xiaoping"
    },
    {
      "question": "David Harris founded an organization called The Resistance to assist in this action. Ted Nugent took meth and urinated on himself in order to commit this action, while James Fallows committed it by lowering his body weight. Joining the Coast Guard and moving to Canada were common methods of performing this action, which led to the arrest of Muhammad Ali. Gerald Ford issued amnesty for those who committed, for ten points, what action instead of fighting in Vietnam?",
      "answer": [
        "dodging the draft during the Vietnam War",
        "equivalent answers that specifically mention the draft"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was briefly restored to power by Zhang Xun. This man benefited from the Articles of Favourable Treatment, though that was revised following a coup by Feng Yuxiang. Prince Zaifeng ruled as a regent for this man, who was tutored in his early years by Reginald Johnston. This man, who was forced to abdicate at age 6, was the subject of a Bernardo Bertolucci biopic that detailed his path from Cixi’s successor to puppet leader of Manchukuo. For ten points, name this final emperor of China.",
      "answer": [
        "Puyi",
        "Xuantong Emperor"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, the ambassador Mikelis was shot trying to board the Guerrier, prompting the Asia to open fire. Prime Minister Wellington sacked this battle’s winning commander, who had controversially provoked a showdown by anchoring his fleet across from the losing side’s horseshoe formation once reinforcements from Henri de Rigny and Lodewijk [lode-veek] Heyden arrived. This battle, which was prompted by the losing side’s decision to reject the Treaty of London, featured an allied fleet under Edward Codrington defeating the Ottoman navy. For ten points, name this decisive 1827 battle of the Greek War of Independence.",
      "answer": "Battle of Navarino"
    },
    {
      "question": "This government permitted the “red seal ships” to trade with Southeast Asia. This government’s Bakumatsu period, which began after the Convention of Kanagawa was signed, reversed the sakoku-era policy of isolationism. Matthew Perry negotiated with this government, which ended with the restoration of the emperor in the Meiji era. For ten points, name this final feudal shogunate of Japan which was founded in 1600 by Ieyasu.",
      "answer": "Tokugawa Shogunate"
    },
    {
      "question": "An ally of this man named George Dew sacked Guayaquil, Ecuador, and they spent much of 1691 harassing a French fort on the Piscataqua River. This Scotsman, who led the Adventure Galley, was given a letter of marque from William III to curb piracy in the southern Indian Ocean. After this man captured the Quedagh Merchant in 1698, the English feared retribution in India and branded him a pirate. For ten points, name this captain of the Blessed William, the only pirate known to have actually buried treasure.",
      "answer": "William Kidd"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man rescued W.J. Walsh from drowning while posted on the Tonopah. Between 1949 and 1953, this man served as Plebiscite Administrator for Jammu and Kashmir. In Operation Galvanic, this man led the campaign to recapture the Gilbert Islands and he was made “Commander in Chief, Pacific Ocean Areas.” This admiral’s intelligence teams discovered a Japanese attack on Midway, leading to the destruction of four Japanese carriers. A class of nuclear aircraft carriers is named for, for ten points, what American World War II fleet admiral?",
      "answer": "Chester William Nimitz, Sr."
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader controversially canceled the GSOMIA intelligence-sharing agreement during a trade dispute with Japan. This man, who served in a support role during Operation Paul Bunyan, defeated Hong Jun-pyo in an election to succeed acting leader Hwang Kyo-ahn after a scandal involving the daughter of a shamanistic cult extorting bribes. The Singapore summit between Donald Trump and Kim Jong Un was mediated by, for ten points, what man who succeeded the impeached Park Geun-hye in 2017 as president of South Korea?",
      "answer": "Moon Jae-in"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the aftermath of one of these events, 231 Koreans were killed by mobs for allegedly causing it. The ruins of the Carmo Convent still stand after being damaged by one of these events in 1755, the first of these events to be scientifically analyzed. An early Chinese device for detecting these events featured dragons that dropped bronze balls into the mouths of toads. San Francisco's Chinatown was destroyed by one of these events in 1906 which also sparked devastating fires. For ten points, name these natural disasters in which the earth's surface shifts.",
      "answer": [
        "Earthquakes",
        "1923 Great Kanto earthquake",
        "1755 Great Lisbon earthquake",
        "1906 San Francisco earthquake 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Failed speculation on this commodity from Peru led to the self-proclaimed Emperor Norton losing his fortune. A movement named for “Five Pecks of [this commodity]” began when Zhang Daoling claimed to see a vision in which he was commanded to build a “new state.” Innovations in producing this crop, sometimes grown on terraces, caused the population growth of Song China. For ten points, name this food grown in paddies and often eaten in its grain form.",
      "answer": "Rice"
    },
    {
      "question": "These people failed to overwhelm European forces who were using the laager, or wagon fort, strategy during the Battle of Blood River. Conquests by these people led to the Mfecane [[MM-feh-KAH-nee]], or “the Crushing,” a period of mass migration of Nguni [[nn- GOO-nee]] people. These people often pincered their opponents using the \"Horn of the Buffalo” formation, implemented by their impi regiments. For ten points, name this Southern African people, once led by King Shaka.",
      "answer": [
        "Zulu people or amaZulu",
        "Zulu Kingdom",
        "Zulu Empire"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The lynching of Thomas Shipp and Abram Smith in this state motivated Abel Meeropol to pen the song \"Strange Fruit.\" The abduction and killing of Madge Oberholtzer by this state's Klan leader, D.C. Stephenson, led to a sharp decline in the second KKK's membership. A Republican senator representing this state interrupted the two non- consecutive terms of Grover Cleveland by winning the Election of 1888. Benjamin Harrison and his grandfather William Henry Harrison both governed, for ten points, which Midwestern state?",
      "answer": "Indiana"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this war, one participant revoked their ambassador in Sweden for openly harboring deserters. Mark Satin wrote a \"Manual\" which taught men how to integrate into Canadian society during this war, and Arlo Guthrie recounts traveling to Whitehall Street in New York and intentionally acting mentally ill in the protest song \"Alice's Restaurant Massacree.\" Men like Bill Clinton and Dick Cheney faced accusations of dodging, for ten points, what 1960s and 1970s conflict in Southeast Asia?",
      "answer": [
        "Vietnam War",
        "Second Indochina War"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Black Panthers inspired a party composed and named for this group which led a renaissance of Maharashtra-based literature and fine arts in the 1970s. The term Harijan, which translates to \"Children of God,\" was used to refer to this group of people in the early 20th century. Under the influence of Rajiv Gandhi, one parliament passed the Prevention of Atrocities Act in an attempt to halt discrimination against this class of people. Mohandas Gandhi was an advocate for, for ten points, which ostracized class of the Indian caste system?",
      "answer": [
        "Untouchables",
        "the Dalits",
        "the Scheduled Caste",
        "the Dalit Panthers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Together with Shigeru Honjo, this man suppressed rebels in the February 26 Incident. This man earned the nickname \"Razor\" for his sharp mind while serving as head of the Kwantung Army. This man's speech on national radio announcing the start of one conflict ended with a rendition of \"Across the Sea.\" After the fall of Saipan, this man was forced to resign his highest office, and he was later executed for war crimes committed while in that office. For ten points, name this prime minister of Japan during most of World War Two.",
      "answer": "Hideki Tojo or Tojo Hideki"
    },
    {
      "question": "While being investigated by the Lytton Commission, this noble recorded that he hoped to ask the namesake official for asylum in interwar Britain but instead was cowed by Seishirō Itagaki. Yuan Shikai [[SHEE-KYE]] succeeded this royal after his regent, Empress Dowager Longyu, issued the abdication edict in 1912. Imperial Japan placed this monarch on the throne of their puppet state, Manchukuo [[mahn-CHOO-kwoh]]. The last monarch of China was, for ten points, which child-ruler known as the Xuantong Emperor?",
      "answer": [
        "Puyi or Yaozhi",
        "Xuantong Emperor before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The killing of a sacred beast begins this nation's king-making ceremony, the Incwala, which coincides with the summer solstice. This nation's head of state was censured by Amnesty International after seizing 18-year-old schoolgirl Zena Mahlangu from her home. This nation's King Sobhuza II designed its flag, which depicts a black and white shield with multiple spears protruding from its side. For ten points, name this tiny kingdom between South Africa and Mozambique, ruled since 1986 by Mswati III.",
      "answer": "Kingdom of eSwatini or Kingdom of Swaziland"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this war, the French captured Minorca [min-OR-cuh], which was returned at its end.\nSaltykov [SALT-yuh-koff] and Loudon [loo-dohn] dealt a heavy loss to the Prussians at\nKunersdorf [KOON-urs-dorf] in this war in which Rossbach [ROSS-bock] and Leuthen [LOYtunn] were sites of victories by Frederick the Great. Canada became a British colony after the\nTreaty of Paris that ended this war. For 10 points, name this worldwide war that lasted from\n1756 to 1763.",
        "answer": [
          "Seven Years’ War",
          "Seven Years’",
          "French and Indian War",
          "French and Indian",
          "Third Carnatic War",
          "Third Carnatic"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A theater of the Seven Years’ War called the Third Carnatic War took place in which\nmodern-day country?",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of India",
          "India",
          "Bharat Ganarajya",
          "Bharat"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man led a parade of 50,000 through the streets of New York City after a 1920\ninternational convention at Liberty Hall. He was indicted for mail fraud in connection with the\nBlack Star Line, a shipping line he created under the Universal Negro Improvement Association.\nFor 10 points, name this Jamaican political leader who promoted Pan-Africanism and a return to\nAfrica.",
        "answer": [
          "Marcus Mosiah Garvey",
          "Garvey",
          "Marcus Garvey"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This religion, which worships Haile Selassie, regards Marcus Garvey as a prophet.",
        "answer": [
          "Rastafarianism",
          "Rasta",
          "Rastafari",
          "Rastafarians"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Cardwell military reforms took place under this man. This politician signed the treaty of Kilmainham with Charles Parnell, and he used his own money to save “fallen women.” The Bulgarian horrors were denounced in the Midlothian campaign of this politician who was ousted by Lord Salisbury following the death of “Chinese” Gordon. This supporter of Irish Home Rule was less liked by Queen Victoria than his liberal rival. For ten points, name this conservative Prime Minister and heated rival of Benjamin Disraeli.",
        "answer": "William Gladstone"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "”Chinese” Gordon’s death in this country, which faced the Mahdist uprising, was a severe blow to Gladstone’s political career.",
        "answer": "Sudan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Shortly before this man’s death, he sent an unsuccessful punitive expedition against the Singhasari kingdom of Java. This man was victorious in the Toluid war against his brother, Ariq Boke, though his attempts to conquer Japan were thwarted by the “divine wind,” kamikaze. The Italian explorer Marco Polo visited this ruler’s capital of Dadu, located in modern day Beijing. For ten points, name this founder of the Yuan Dynasty in China and grandson of Genghis Khan.",
        "answer": "Kublai Khan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Kublai Khan ordered three invasions into this country, led by the Tran dynasty and the Champa, both of which agreed to become Mongol vassals. In the 19th century, the Nguyen dynasty led this Southeast Asian country.",
        "answer": "Vietnam"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Aspartofthisevent,theMeirokushasocietypromoted“civilizationandenlightenment.”Lawsenacted during this period included tax reform that returned land to the government and the replacement of the han system with prefectures. A group of reforms during this period were outlined in the Charter Oath. In this period, a group of daimyo fought the Boshin War against the government, and the Satsuma Rebellion was launched by discontented samurai. For ten points, name this period of 19th century modernization in Japan in which the emperor was restored to power.",
        "answer": [
          "Meiji Restoration",
          "equivalents for restoration",
          "descriptions of the Meiji era",
          "government"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Meiji Restoration began after the appearance of these colorful objects, led by Commodore Matthew Perry, which forced Japan to sign the Convention of Kanagawa.",
        "answer": "the black ships or the kurofune"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This program’s effects were first tested at an artificial community in Chayashan, where all wages were replaced by “work points.” Sparrows were systematically killed in this program, as the government sought to eliminate the “Four Pests.” 30 million people may have perished in the world’s deadliest famine as a result of this program, which encouraged farmers to establish backyard steel furnaces. For ten points, name this 1958 initiative in which Mao Zedong attempted to industrialize China.",
        "answer": [
          "Great Leap Forward",
          "da yue jin",
          "Second Five Year Plan"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Great Leap Forward ran concurrently with this other program, in which Mao Zedong invited others to criticize his policies. Later, he abruptly turned course and jailed the “rightist” dissidents.",
        "answer": [
          "Hundred Flowers movement",
          "Baihua yundong"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man accidentally sunk John Tyler’s attempts to annex Texas after a letter to Richard Pakenham hoping for the expansion of slavery was exposed. While serving as James Monroe’s Secretary for War, this man successfully set up the Bureau of Indian Affairs. This man penned an “Exposition and Protest” condemning the Tariff of Abominations, arguing that states should have a right to nullify federal laws. For ten points, name this member of the Great Triumvirate from South Carolina.",
        "answer": "John C. Calhoun"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During Calhoun’s vice presidency, his wife Floride provoked this scandal by refusing to speak with the Secretary of War’s wife over allegations of adultery.",
        "answer": [
          "Petticoat Affair",
          "Peggy Eaton Affair"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A civil war of these people resulted in John of Giscala massacring Ananus’ followers. To win a battle against these people, government forces rolled a siege tower up a dirt ramp to avoid traversing the well-defended “snake road.” Shortly after he was victorious at the siege of Yodfat, Vespasian hired one of these people, Josephus, as his biographer. A faction of these people committed mass suicide atop Masada fortress rather than surrender, leading them to be known as the Zealots. For ten points, name this religious group that tried to expel the Romans from Jerusalem.",
        "answer": [
          "Jewish people",
          "Zealots before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This emperor’s capture of Jerusalem was celebrated in an arch erected by his brother Domitian. Despite his campaigns, this emperor would later cause controversy by marrying a Jewish queen, Berenice.",
        "answer": [
          "Titus",
          "Titus Flavius Caesar Vespasianus Augustus, but do not"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This site was once believed to have been imported from Africa for use in healing, then transported from Mount Killaraus after a long battle. In 1915, this site was sold for 6000 pounds to Cecil Chubbs, who then donated it. This site is surrounded by “aubrey holes” speculated to have once contained bluestones; earlier historians speculated this site was a center of Druidic worship. For ten points, name this prehistoric site near Salisbury consisting of standing rocks.",
        "answer": "Stonehenge"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Most of the bluestones of Stonehenge are made of dolerite, which is this type of rock. Ireland’s Giant’s Causeway is made of thousands of columns of basalt, another example of this type of rock.",
        "answer": "igneous rock"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Forces of this dynasty won the Battle of Liaoluo Bay over Dutch East India Company ships by using fireships. During this dynasty’s Jiaqing Emperor, Wokou pirate raids intensified, and despite earlier passing the Haijin laws under the Hongwu Emperor, this dynasty still led seven Treasure Voyages. The eunuch Zheng He led voyages for this dynasty. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty that preceded the Qing [ching] and is commonly known for its porcelain vases.",
        "answer": "Ming Dynasty"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Ming Dynasty was established in the wake of this rebellion, which was inspired by the White Lotus Society.",
        "answer": [
          "Red Turban Rebellion",
          "Hongjin Qiyi"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler allegedly threw a group of fettered Jews into the Dead Sea to test its buoyancy after destroying Jericho. This ruler seized power by joining forces with the Syrian governor Mucianus, who encouraged this man to implement his toilet tax. This man met Josephus, whom he would later patronize, while putting down the first Jewish rebellion in AD 66. For ten points, name this first Flavian emperor who ended the Year of the Four Emperors.",
        "answer": "Vespasian"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shortly before his death, Vespasian sent this general to govern Britannia and conquer Wales, which he summarily did. This man’s deeds were recorded by Tacitus, his son-in-law.",
        "answer": "Gnaeus Julius Agricola"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire’s forces failed to restore Le Chieu Thong to power in Vietnam after the Tay Son Rebellion. This dynasty reformed its military with the help of Zeng Guofeng and Li Hongzhang in the Self-Strengthening Movement. The Old Summer Palace was burned during this dynasty. Hong Xiuquan, who believed himself to be Jesus’s brother, led the Taiping Rebellion against this dynasty, which aided the Boxer Rebellion against foreigners in 1900. For ten points, name this last imperial Chinese dynasty.",
        "answer": [
          "Qing Dynasty",
          "Manchu Dynasty"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Empress Dowager declared war on foreign invaders during the Boxer Rebellion, but later softened her stance against foreign influence in the capital.",
        "answer": "Empress Dowager Cixi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader was aided by the militaristic Blue Shirts Society in enforcing traditional values during the New Life Movement. After this leader was kidnapped in the Xi’an [shee-ahn] incident, he was strong-armed into forming a “Second United Front” to fight Japan. This successor of Sun Yat-sen established a government in Taiwan after losing a civil war to the Communists. For ten points, name this Nationalist leader who was defeated by Mao Zedong.",
        "answer": "Chiang Kai-shek"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Xi’an Incident took place as Japan’s Kwantung Army, whose leader included this man, occupied Manchuria and threatened war with China. This man later served as Japan’s Minister of War and Prime Minister during most of World War II.",
        "answer": "Hideki Tojo"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A “Little” version of this event was presided over by W.G. Boshoff and saw one target say “My Lord, I am a professional agitator.” Percy Yutar was the chief prosecutor during this event, in which one side was defended by Bram Fischer. A defendant in this trial claimed that the Sharpeville Massacre justified the use of force by the oppressed in a three-hour-long speech given by a man who declared “I am prepared to die.” For ten points, name this trial in which Nelson Mandela was sentenced to life imprisonment in 1964.",
        "answer": "Rivonia Trial"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Many of the defendants in the Rivonia Trial were members of this group, the armed wing of the African National Congress, that formed in the wake of the Sharpeville Massacre.",
        "answer": [
          "Umkhonto we Sizwe",
          "Spear of the Nation"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle may have featured a “paratrooper putsch” in which Pierre Langlais seized command. Charles Piroth killed himself with a grenade after his artillery failed to hit targets in the hills in this battle. Outposts named Gabrielle and Beatrice were overrun during this battle, leading the losers to sign the 1954 Geneva Accords and leave Indochina. For ten points, name this battle in which Viet Minh forces ousted the French from Vietnam.",
        "answer": "Battle of Dien Bien Phu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Vietnamese general surrounded the French at Dien Bien Phu and led the successful siege.",
        "answer": "V˜o Nguyˆen Gi´ap"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After the 1960 Sharpeville massacre, this organization established the uMkhonto we Sizwe [[oom-KOHN-toh weh SEEZ-weh]], or \"Spear of the Nation.\" The Spear of the Nation was founded by a man who gave his “I Am Prepared to Die” speech at the Rivonia Trial, which sent members of this organization to a prison on Robben Island. This organization elected Cyril Ramaphosa as president in 2017, the year before he was also elected president of South Africa. For ten points, name this South African political party once led by Nelson Mandela.",
        "answer": [
          "African National Congress",
          "ANC"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Cyril Ramaphosa served as secretary general to Nelson Mandela and deputy president to this former South African president who resigned in 2018 after a parliamentary vote of no confidence.",
        "answer": [
          "Jacob Zuma",
          "Msholozi"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The town of Kent, New York is home to the largest indoor statue of this figure in the West. A statue of this figure faces the Kala Wewa reservoir in the village of Avukana [[AH- vue-KAH-nah]]. The largest stone statue of this figure was built to protect sailors at the confluence of the Min and Dadu Rivers. This figure is depicted sitting in a half-lotus position in a 302-foot tall statue in Thailand. For ten points, name this ancient Indian religious figure, who was formerly depicted at Bamiyan.",
        "answer": [
          "Buddha",
          "Siddartha Gautama,",
          "either underlined word",
          "Maitreya",
          "Great Buddha",
          "Avukana Buddha",
          "Leshan Giant Buddha"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The historical Buddha is traditionally believed to have been born in what is today this Himalayan nation.",
        "answer": "Federal Democratic Republic of Nepal"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This figure took inspiration from the writings of anarchist and fellow countryman Ricardo Flores Magón to adopt the slogan \"Tierra y Libertad.\" Under the guise of a meeting, Jesús Guajardo [[gwah-HAR-doh]] assassinated this resident of Morelos state in 1919 on the orders of Venustiano Carranza. This man, who met with Pancho Villa at the Aguascalientes Convention of 1914, led the Liberation Army of the South against the government of Francisco Madero. For ten points, name this agrarian revolutionary during the Mexican Revolution.",
        "answer": "Emiliano Zapata"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Zapata names an agrarian movement in modern Mexico which originally formed to oppose this 1994 treaty, which created Free Trade Zones with Mexico's northern neighbors.",
        "answer": [
          "NAFTA",
          "North American Free Trade Agreement"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A monarch from this dynasty patronized the Fatawa 'Alamgiri law code as part of a personal religious revival that included becoming a hafiz. This dynasty, which was the last regime to destroy the Vishwanath Temple, scaled back religious tolerance by executing Tegh Bahadur, a Sikh guru, and reinstituting the jizya tax under its emperor Aurangzeb. For ten points, name this Muslim dynasty that ruled north India following the 1520s conquests of Babur.",
        "answer": "Mughal Dynasty or the Mughals"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 1640s, the Mughals began to lose control of huge portions of central India when the Hindu king Shivaji established which empire based in the Deccan Plateau and came to dominate much of central and northern India?",
        "answer": "Maratha Empire or Maratha Confederacy"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "RISE OF JAPAN",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The title of the de facto military rulers of feudal Japan?",
          "answer": [
            "shogun",
            "seii tai shogun"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The military class banned from carrying swords and then abolished during modernization?",
          "answer": "samurai"
        },
        {
          "question": "The emperor who launched a namesake period of modernization?",
          "answer": [
            "Meiji",
            "Meiji Emperor",
            "Meiji tenno Mutsuhito",
            "Mutsuhito"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The other Asian power which Japan defeated in an 1894-5 war?",
          "answer": [
            "China",
            "Zhongguo",
            "Qing",
            "Qing dynasty",
            "Qing Chao",
            "Empire of the Great Qing",
            "Da Qing Diguo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The peninsular country annexed by Japan in 1910, ending its Choson Dynasty?",
          "answer": [
            "Korea",
            "Hanguk"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The crushing naval victory by Japan over Russia in 1905?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Tsushima Strait",
            "Tsushima",
            "Battle of Tsushima"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The port gained on the Liaodong peninsula by Japan after the Russo-Japanese War?",
          "answer": [
            "Port Arthur",
            "Dalian"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The treaty ending the Russo-Japanese War signed in a New Hampshire city?",
          "answer": [
            "Treaty of Portsmouth",
            "Portsmouth"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Who or what was..."
    },
    {
      "category": "JAMESTOWN",
      "prompt": "During the colonization of Jamestown, who or what was…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The man who led the colony through its most difficult times and mapped the Chesapeake Bay in the Discovery?",
          "answer": "John Smith"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Indian princess who converted to Christianity and moved to England before dying of smallpox?",
          "answer": "Pocahontas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Both the term for the Indian Confederacy neighboring Jamestown, and its leader?",
          "answer": "Powhatan"
        },
        {
          "question": "The name of the company which funded Jamestown in hopes of finding gold?",
          "answer": "Virginia Company"
        },
        {
          "question": "The man who began the cultivation of tobacco in Jamestown?",
          "answer": "John Rolfe"
        },
        {
          "question": "The period of time where the colony nearly failed due to lack of supplies?",
          "answer": "Starving Times"
        },
        {
          "question": "The largest of the three ships originally sent to colonize Jamestown?",
          "answer": "Susan Constant"
        },
        {
          "question": "The governor who saved the colony with extra supplies and led the first war against the Indians?",
          "answer": "Third and Twelfth Baron De La Warr"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "AGE OF EXPLORATION",
      "prompt": "Which European explorer…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Discovered the New World in 1492?",
          "answer": "Christopher Columbus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the initial leader of the first ships to circumnavigate the globe but died in the Philippines?",
          "answer": "Ferdinand Magellan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Named Florida while unsuccessfully searching for the Fountain of Youth?",
          "answer": "Juan Ponce de Leon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first to reach India by sea in 1498 by rounding the Cape of Good Hope?",
          "answer": "Vasco da Gama"
        },
        {
          "question": "Reached the Cape of Good Hope but his crew would not let him round it?",
          "answer": "Bartolomeu Dias"
        },
        {
          "question": "In the pay of France explored the North American coast? The entrance to New York harbor was named for him.",
          "answer": "Giovanni da Verrazzano"
        },
        {
          "question": "Launched the age of discovery by funding and supporting Portuguese exploration of the African coast?",
          "answer": "Prince Henry the Navigator"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sailed to Canada for England in 1497?",
          "answer": "John Cabot"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Post-War Japan",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that occupied Japan after World War II.",
          "answer": [
            "United States of America or USA,",
            "America"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Organization that Japan was prevented from having in its new constitution.",
          "answer": [
            "a military",
            "equivalents like armed forces"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Emperor that announced the Japanese surrender with the 1945 Jewel Voice Broadcast.",
          "answer": "Hirohito or Emperor Showa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Son of that emperor, who succeeded him and continues to rule.",
          "answer": "Akihito"
        },
        {
          "question": "Post-war Japanese industry, including Mitsubishi and Toyota, that rivals Detroit’s “Big 3.”",
          "answer": [
            "automobile industry",
            "anything to do with the production of cars"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Major index on the Tokyo Stock Exchange that topped out at nearly 39,000 during the late 80s asset price bubble.",
          "answer": [
            "Nikkei 225",
            "any additional information, such as the Nikkei stock index"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Japanese author who led an attempted coup in 1970 before committing seppuku.",
          "answer": "Yukio Mishima"
        },
        {
          "question": "Economic problem, in which a central bank’s injections of money fail to lower rates, that Japan experienced during the “Lost Decade.”",
          "answer": "liquidity trap"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Famous Ships",
      "prompt": "Name the ship that...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Sunk on its maiden voyage in 1912 after hitting an iceberg, killing well over 1,000 people.",
          "answer": "RMS Titanic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gained the nickname “Old Ironsides” after fighting the Guerriere.",
          "answer": "USS Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was Horatio Nelson’s flagship when he was shot at Trafalgar.",
          "answer": "HMS Victory"
        },
        {
          "question": "Destroyed the Hood at the Battle of Denmark Strait and was sunk three days later.",
          "answer": "Bismarck"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sunk, and is now a memorial, at Pearl Harbor.",
          "answer": "USS Arizona Memorial"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the location of the Japanese surrender after World War II.",
          "answer": "USS Missouri"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sunk in 1945 after delivering the parts for Little Boy.",
          "answer": "USS Indianapolis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Had its entire crew go missing on an 1872 voyage to Genoa.",
          "answer": "Mary Celeste"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Brazil",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Continent divided by the Treaty of Tordesillas, which organized Brazilian colonization.",
          "answer": "South America"
        },
        {
          "question": "National language of Brazil, as a result of its European colonization.",
          "answer": "Portuguese"
        },
        {
          "question": "Businessman who established a company town in Brazil to produce rubber for his company’s Model T’s.",
          "answer": "Henry Ford"
        },
        {
          "question": "Practice partially ended by the Law of the Free Womb and fully ended by the Golden Law.",
          "answer": "slavery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last Emperor of Brazil. He led Brazil to victory in the War of the Triple Alliance.",
          "answer": "Dom Pedro II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Substance that, with milk, names a period of rule by landowners in Sao Paulo and Minas Gerais.",
          "answer": [
            "coffee or caf´e",
            "caf´e com leite politics, rule, etc."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader who established Brazil’s Estado Novo regime in 1930.",
          "answer": "Getulio Vargas"
        },
        {
          "question": "1851-52 war in which Brazil defeated the Juan Manuel de Rosas-led Argentine Confederation to gain power over a major river basin.",
          "answer": "Platine War"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Colonial India",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country whose Indian territories were annexed after the Seven Years War; its East India Company was founded by Jean-Baptiste Colbert",
          "answer": "Kingdom of France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nonviolent leader who protested British rule with a salt march to Dandi.",
          "answer": "Mohandas Gandhi or Mahatma Gandhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region where the British conquest of India began; the region around its namesake bay is divided between India and Bangladesh",
          "answer": [
            "Bengal",
            "Bay of Bengal"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1857 mutiny of native Indian soldiers that ended company rule in India.",
          "answer": "Sepoy Mutiny or Uprising, Revolt, etc."
        },
        {
          "question": "1756 incident in which several British East India Company employees died in a crowded prison cell.",
          "answer": "Black Hole of Calcutta"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where Reginald Dyer’s men fired into a crowd of pilgrims in 1919, killing hundreds.",
          "answer": "Amritsar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rocket-loving Indian state ruled by Tipu Sultan and conquered by the British in the 19th century.",
          "answer": "Mysore"
        },
        {
          "question": "Doctrine that allowed Britain to take control of princely states whose rulers had no male heir.",
          "answer": "Doctrine of Lapse"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Apartheid",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Party led by Nelson Mandela that took over South Africa’s government after the fall of apartheid.",
          "answer": [
            "African National Congress",
            "ANC"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Language spoken, alongside English, by South Africa’s formerly dominant white minority.",
          "answer": "Afrikaans"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bantu ethnic group that, along with the Zulu, made up most of South Africa’s black majority.",
          "answer": [
            "Xhosa , with a lateral click at the start",
            "be lenient"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "President who brokered the end of apartheid and shared the Nobel Peace Prize with Mandela.",
          "answer": "Fredrik Willem de Klerk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island on which Mandela was imprisoned for 27 years.",
          "answer": "Robben Island"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trial at which Nelson Mandela gave his “I am prepared to die” speech.",
          "answer": "Rivonia Trial"
        },
        {
          "question": "Militant anti-apartheid group, the armed wing of Mandela’s political party, that formed in 1961.",
          "answer": "Spear of the Nation or Umkhonto we Sizwe"
        },
        {
          "question": "Farm where Mandela hid while being pursued by police.",
          "answer": "Lilliesleaf Farm"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Second Sino-Japanese War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Mountain range between China and India that Allied pilots flew over to supply Chinese forces.",
          "answer": "Himalayan Mountains"
        },
        {
          "question": "Five-member body of the United Nations that China was admitted to during the war.",
          "answer": "UN Security Council"
        },
        {
          "question": "War between the Nationalists and Communists that was paused by the war against Japan.",
          "answer": "Chinese Civil War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of the Republic of China, the site of a 1937 massacre.",
          "answer": "Nanjing or Nanking"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Lady who visited America several times to rally support for her husband’s war effort.",
          "answer": [
            "Soong Mei-ling",
            "Madame Chiang"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1931 incident involving dynamite near a railway that led to a Japanese invasion of Manchuria.",
          "answer": [
            "Mukden incident",
            "Liutiaohu incident"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Bridge southwest of Beijing where a 1937 incident marked the start of the war.",
          "answer": "Marco Polo Bridge or Lugou Bridge"
        },
        {
          "question": "Major 1944 Japanese offensive aimed at opening a land route to Indochina, after which Joseph Stilwell was removed.",
          "answer": "Operation Ichi-Go"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Hakka People",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Asian island with capital at Taipei where Hakka dialects are widely spoken.",
          "answer": "Taiwan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Largest river of Northern China, from whose basin the Hakka likely migrated south.",
          "answer": [
            "Yellow River",
            "Huang He"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Series of wars with Britain in the 19th century in which Hakka generals played a leading role in the Qing navy.",
          "answer": "Opium Wars"
        },
        {
          "question": "Custom the Hakka refused to take part in, in which a certain body part was crushed to assume a “lotus” shape.",
          "answer": [
            "footbinding",
            "word forms and equivalents"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Trek across China, conducted mostly by Hakka soldiers after Communist defeats in battle in 1934.",
          "answer": "Long March"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where Hakka soldiers fought a Japanese siege during the Defense of Sihang Warehouse.",
          "answer": "Shanghai"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Taiping Rebellion whose army was mostly made up of Hakka.",
          "answer": "Hong Xiuquan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Circular clan houses, often several stories high, in which Hakka people traditionally live.",
          "answer": "tulou"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "African Civil Wars",
      "prompt": "Name the country where...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Muammar Gaddafi was killed after the fall of Tripoli.",
          "answer": "Libya"
        },
        {
          "question": "The overthrow of Siad Barre led to the Battle of Mogadishu.",
          "answer": "Somalia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jose Eduardo dos Santos led the MPLA against UNITA in a former Portuguese colony.",
          "answer": "Angola"
        },
        {
          "question": "A Marxist-Leninist state was established after the Derg overthrew Haile Selassie.",
          "answer": "Ethiopia"
        },
        {
          "question": "The sieges of Barentu and Massawa led to independence from the previous answer.",
          "answer": "Eritrea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prince Johnson brutally murdered Samuel Doe.",
          "answer": "Liberia"
        },
        {
          "question": "RENAMO conducted a 15-year rebellion against the leftist FRELIMO.",
          "answer": "Mozambique"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ansumane Man´e led a coup against the government of Jo˜ao Bernardo Vieira in 1998.",
          "answer": "Guinea-Bissau"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The British Raj",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "British Queen who was proclaimed Empress of India in 1876.",
          "answer": "Queen Victoria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Year in which the Raj ended with the partition of Pakistan and India.",
          "answer": "1947"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nonviolent leader who opposed a partition along religious lines and was assassinated by Nathruam Godse.",
          "answer": "Mohandas Gandhi or Mahatma Gandhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "1857 mutiny of Indian infantrymen that ended British East India Company control of India.",
          "answer": "Sepoy Mutiny"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for the over 500 vassal states that existed in India by the time the Raj ended.",
          "answer": [
            "princely states",
            "native states",
            "feudatory states"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1916 power sharing agreement between the Muslim League and Indian National Congress, signed in Uttar Pradesh.",
          "answer": "Lucknow Pact"
        },
        {
          "question": "Viceroy of India from 1916 to 1921 who worked with Edwin Samuel Montagu on constitutional reforms; he was in charge during the Amritsar Massacre.",
          "answer": [
            "Lord Chelmsford or Viscount Chelmsford",
            "Frederick John Napier Thesiger"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Three Kingdoms Period",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that was divided during the Three Kingdoms Period.",
          "answer": [
            "China",
            "Zhongguo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty whose collapse in 220 AD gave way to the period.",
          "answer": "Han Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "184 AD rebellion, started by Zhang Jiao, that hastened the downfall of that dynasty.",
          "answer": [
            "Yellow Turban Rebellion",
            "Yellow Scarves Rebellion",
            "Huangjin zhi luan"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Family that ruled the state of Wu and claimed descent from the author of the Art of War.",
          "answer": "Sun"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty, founded by Sima Yan, that ended the period by conquering Eastern Wu.",
          "answer": "Jin dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "208 AD naval battle, a defeat for Wei, that laid the groundwork for the later establishment of the Kingdom of Shu.",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Red Cliffs",
            "Battle of Chibi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Shu minister and renowned strategist who formed a rivalry with Sima Yi; he died at the Battle of Wuzhang Plains.",
          "answer": [
            "Zhuge Liang",
            "Kongming"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Warlord who seized control of Luoyang in 189 AD, was the target of a coalition a year later, and was assassinated by Lu¨ Bu.",
          "answer": [
            "Dong Zhuo",
            "Zhongying"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Han Dynasty",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country the Han dynasty controlled from Chang'an and later Luoyang",
          "answer": [
            "China",
            "Zhongguo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion legendarily founded by Lao Tsu whose members revolted during the Han",
          "answer": [
            "Taoism or Daoism",
            "or Daojiao"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Rebellion led by Zhang Jiao and named for colorful headwear which weakened the dynasty",
          "answer": [
            "Yellow Turban Rebellion",
            "Yellow Scarves"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The Han established this trade route, named for a natural fiber used to make fine cloth",
          "answer": "Silk Road"
        },
        {
          "question": "Numbered period of civil war that followed the fall of the Han and included clashes between Cao Cao, Sun Jian, and Liu Bei",
          "answer": "Three Kingdoms or Sanguo Shidai"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty founded by Wang Mang which temporarily interrupted the Han.",
          "answer": "Xin ] Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pair of Vietnamese sisters who rebelled against the Han Dynasty in 40 CE.",
          "answer": "Trung Sisters or Trung Trac and Trung Nhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Warlord who employed Lu Bu and seized power after deposing Liu Bian",
          "answer": [
            "Dong Zhuo",
            "either",
            "both names",
            "Zhongying 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Japan in World War Two",
      "prompt": "Concerning Imperial Japan's war effort in World War Two, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Emperor of Japan during the war?",
          "answer": "Hirohito or Shōwa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Long-range carrier-based fighter planes that were used in most of Japan's naval battles?",
          "answer": "Zero"
        },
        {
          "question": "Initial commander-in-chief of naval forces for Japan in the War of the Pacific.",
          "answer": "Isoroku Yamamoto"
        },
        {
          "question": "American battleship on which the formal instrument of surrender was signed on September 2, 1945?",
          "answer": "USS Missouri"
        },
        {
          "question": "Skirmish outside of Beijing that started the Japanese invasion of China?",
          "answer": "Marco Polo Bridge Incident"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name for the emperor's recorded announcement of initial surrender?",
          "answer": "Jewel Voice broadcast"
        },
        {
          "question": "Enormous, multi-industry conglomerates mostly broken up after the war?",
          "answer": "Zaibatsu or Financial Cliques"
        },
        {
          "question": "Late 1944 major offensive in China to open a land route to French Indochina?",
          "answer": "Operation Ichi-Go"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Han Dynasty",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Han Dynasty, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Large East Asian country whose primary ethnic group is named for the Han.",
          "answer": [
            "China",
            "Empire of China",
            "or Imperial China",
            "Zhōngguó",
            "People's Republic of China/a]",
            "PRC"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Royal title created by Qin [[CHIN] Shi Huang, which the Han assumed in 202 BC.",
          "answer": "Emperor of China or Huángdì"
        },
        {
          "question": "Technology traditionally attributed to court official Cai Lun, who used pulp from the mulberry tree.",
          "answer": "Paper or Papermaking"
        },
        {
          "question": "Period which followed the collapse of the Han Dynasty, witnessing warfare between the states of Wei, Shu, and Wu.",
          "answer": "Three Kingdoms Period or Sānguó Shídài"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massive 184 AD peasant revolt named for the garment worn by its participants.",
          "answer": [
            "Yellow Turban Rebellion",
            "Yellow Scarves Rebellion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Confucian scholar and court official who briefly interrupted the Han with his own Xin [[SHIN]] Dynasty.",
          "answer": [
            "Wang Mang",
            "Jujun"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of the Han dynasty who defeated the Chu at Gaixia [[\"GUY\"-SHAH]] to become sole ruler.",
          "answer": [
            "Liu Bang",
            "Emperor Gao",
            "or Gaozu of Han",
            "or Gaodi",
            "or Taizu"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Traditional name of Xi'an, which served as the capital of the Han dynasty.",
          "answer": "Chang'an"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Portuguese Empire",
      "prompt": "During the founding of the Portuguese Empire, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Prince who funded voyages around the coast of West Africa.",
          "answer": [
            "Henry the Navigator or Henrique, o Navegador",
            "Infante Dom Henrique"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Geographical feature at the southern end of Africa first reached by explorer Bartolomeu Dias in 1488.",
          "answer": "Cape of Good Hope or Cabo da Boa Esperança"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colony first reached by Pedro Cabral while trying to sail around Africa.",
          "answer": "Brazil or Brasil"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chinese port city on the Pearl River ceded to Portugal in 1557.",
          "answer": "Macau or Macao"
        },
        {
          "question": "African kingdom aided by the Portuguese against the Adal Sultanate and the Ottomans.",
          "answer": "Ethiopia or Abyssinia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Indian city captured by the Portuguese in 1510 and turned into the capital of Portuguese India.",
          "answer": "Goa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Portuguese admiral who led the 1511 capture of Malacca and died immediately after his capture of Hormuz.",
          "answer": "Afonso de Albuquerque"
        },
        {
          "question": "Central African kingdom under influence of the Portuguese, later incorporated into the colony of Angola.",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Kongo or Reino do Congo",
            "or Kongo dya Ntotila"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "October Crisis",
      "prompt": "During the October Crisis, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Canadian province where French-speaking secessionism led to the October Crisis.",
          "answer": "Québec"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime minister of Canada during the crisis who is the father of prime minister Justin.",
          "answer": "Pierre Trudeau or Pierre Yves Elliott Trudeau"
        },
        {
          "question": "City whose stock exchange and city hall were bombed during the crisis, as well as the home of its mayor Jean Drapeau.",
          "answer": "Montreal"
        },
        {
          "question": "French president who controversially promoted sectarian nationalism in Canada during his trip to Expo 67.",
          "answer": "Charles de Gaulle or Charles André Joseph Marie de Gaulle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Terrorist group whose bombings of public buildings started the October Crisis.",
          "answer": [
            "FLQ",
            "the Front de libération du Québec"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Phrase uttered by the prime minister when asked how far he would go to end the crisis.",
          "answer": "\"Just watch me.\" or \"Well, just watch me.\""
        },
        {
          "question": "Law invoked during the Crisis which suspended civil liberties.",
          "answer": "War Measures Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Deputy premier kidnapped and murdered at the height of the crisis.",
          "answer": "Pierre Laporte"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first meeting of this political party ended with \"three cheers for the Queen Empress.\" One prime minister from this party died in Tashkent the day after reaching a\npeace agreement with a neighboring country. That leader's successor, also from this party,\ndeclared a (20 pts) ",
        "state of emergency in 1975, after which this party lost an election to Morarji\n[more-are-jee] Desai's Janata Party. Three generations of politicians from this party have\nbeen (10 pts) ",
        "prime minister, beginning with Jawaharlal [juh-wah-har-lull] Nehru. For 10 points,\nname this political party that led the Indian independence movement."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Indian National Congress",
        "Congress",
        "Congress Party",
        "INC"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A document opposing this policy begins, “The People Shall Govern!”. That Freedom Charter was drawn up in a 1955 Congress of the People by Z.K. Matthews and (20 pts)",
        "Lionel Bernstein, among other activists against this policy, which led its country to recognize the TBVC states. This policy officially began with the 1948 election of the Reunited (10 pts)",
        "National Party under D. F. Malan. This policy’s Terrorism Act led to Steve Biko’s [bee-kohs] death in police custody, and it was opposed by Nelson Mandela. For 10 points, name this policy of South African racial segregation."
      ],
      "answer": "apartheid"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This object’s advantages were mitigated after a specimen was found on Akutan in the Aleutian Islands, and the Thach Weave was another countermeasure developed against it. This (20 pts)",
        "vehicle often traveled alongside the G4M “Betty” and was designed to replace the A5M “Claude.” The protagonist of Miyazaki’s The (10 pts)",
        "Wind Rises is most famous for designing this object, which was often launched from ships like the Hiryu and Akagi. For 10 points, identify this Mitsubishi-produced WWII-era Japanese fighter plane."
      ],
      "answer": "Mitsubishi A6M Zero"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Vela Incident was likely a result of one of these programs. One of these programs was exposed by The Sunday Times with the testimony of Mordechai Vanunu. South Africa was the first country to (20 pts)",
        "voluntarily end one of these programs. Another of these programs carried out Operation Smiling Buddha, under the watch of Indira Gandhi. India, (10 pts)",
        "Pakistan, and Israel have refused to sign a treaty banning the proliferation of these programs. For ten points, name this type of military program, one of which claimed success in North Korea in January 2016."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "programs for the development of nuclear weapons",
        "any equivalent for nuclear weapons, including hydrogen bomb before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group created settlements known as “reductions” to convert the Tupi-Guarani in Paraguay. The bull Regimini militantis Ecclesiae approved of this group’s formation, but limited it to 60 members until (20 pts)",
        "Pope Julius III removed that limit. One member of this group, Jean de Br´ebeuf integrated settlers of New France with the Hurons, and members of this group who traveled to (10 pts)",
        "Asia included Matteo Ricci and St. Francis Xavier. The motto “Ad maiorem Dei gloriam” is held by, for ten points, what Catholic counter-reformation group founded by Ignatius of Loyola?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Society of Jesus",
        "Jesuits"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was able to capture Kimpo airfield after landings at Red, Blue, and Green beaches in Operation Chromite. This man was replaced by Matthew Ridgway, despite leading a difficult (20 pts)",
        "landing at Inchon, after a series of disagreements with Harry Truman in the Korean War. In another conflict, this commander vowed “I (10 pts)",
        "shall return” when the Japanese forced him to retreat from the Philippines. For ten points, name this American general who commanded Allied troops in the Pacific Theatre of World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Douglas MacArthur"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) States in this era were grouped into Vertical or Horizontal alliances based on their stance towards the most powerful state. A flourishing of philosophy called the Hundred (20 pts)",
        "Schools of Thought ended with this period. It began after the breakup of the Jin state and occurred during the Eastern Zhou period. This period came after a time of smaller states known as the (10 pts)",
        "Spring and Autumn Period. The great works of Confucianism were compiled during, for ten points, what period of Chinese history that ended when Qin Shi Huangdi unified China?"
      ],
      "answer": "Warring States Period"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. One side in this war outnumbered the other eleven to seven in terms of massive military units called Akshauhini [ahk-shao-hee-nee]. In this war, (20 pts)",
        "Bhishma’s body was shot so full of arrows that he was disabled before his body touched the ground. A charioteer in this eighteen-day battle told his (10 pts)",
        "companion archer that he must not be afraid to face his family in single combat. The Kauravas faced off against the Pandavas in, for ten points, what war in which Krishna advises Arjuna in an Indian epic poem?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kurukshetra War",
        "descriptions of the war or battle, etc. from the Mahabharata and/or the Bhagavad Gita",
        "the war between the Kauravas and Pandavas before “Kauravas” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A few former members of this group gathered intelligence as part of the Kit Carson Scouts. The book People’s War, People’s Army is described as this group’s “Insurrection Manual for (20 pts)",
        "Underdeveloped Countries” and was written by a general who aided both his army and this group with supplies along the Truong Son trail. This group, which was targeted by the Strategic (10 pts)",
        "Hamlet Program, attempted to expand into the Mekong Delta following the Tet Offensive. For ten points, name these communist guerrillas in South Vietnam."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Viet Cong or the National Liberation Front for Southern Vietnam",
        "the People’s Liberation Armed Forces of South Vietnam",
        "the PLAF"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Wei Zheng [“way” zhun] advised this dynasty’s second emperor, Li Shimin [lee sh-ming], also known as Taizong [“tie”-zohn]. The Silla kingdom unified Korea against opposition from this dynasty, whose forces gave up the secret to making (20 pts)",
        "paper after being defeated by Muslim troops at the Talas River. This dynasty’s rule was interrupted by the brief Zhou Dynasty, led by Wu Zetian [woo zuh-tehn], China’s only female emperor. (10 pts)",
        "An Lushan [ahn loo-shahn] launched a revolt against, for ten points, what dynasty that followed the Sui [swee] and ruled during China’s golden age from the 7th to the 10th century?"
      ],
      "answer": "Tang Dynasty"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Canadian Norman Bethune was embedded as a doctor in this man’s army. This man was profiled in the most famous work of Edgar Snow. Five Encirclement (20 pts)",
        "Campaigns attempted and failed to defeat this leader, who compromised with an opponent after that opponent was kidnapped in the (10 pts)",
        "Xi’an [shee-ahn] Incident. This leader moved to a new base in Jiangxi during the Long March. For ten points, name this longtime Chinese communist leader."
      ],
      "answer": "Mao Zedong"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This oration asks its listeners to “keep pace with the progress of the world” after having “resolved to pave the way for a grand peace.” A copy of this oration was kept in a “bank vault” under the palace, preventing the leaders of the 15 August (20 pts)",
        "coup from finding it before it was smuggled out in a laundry basket. This speech concedes that, despite attempts for “self-preservation,” a joint (10 pts)",
        "declaration from China, the United States, and the USSR was accepted, and the speaker and his country must “[endure] the unendurable.” For ten points, name this speech delivered by Emperor Hirohito, announcing Japan’s surrender in World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Jewel Voice Broadcast"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader undertook a radical anti-inflation program despite pledging not to do so in a competitive 1990 election campaign; the program led to what became known as his namesake “shock.” This leader was toppled by the “Vladivideos,” in which (20 pts)",
        "Vladimiro Montesinos admitted to corruption. This leader defeated a guerrilla group led by Abimael Guzman as well as a general election campaign by (10 pts)",
        "Mario Vargas Llosa. This man’s children Keiko and Kenji serve in his country’s senate, despite this man’s imprisonment on corruption charges. For ten points, name this Japanese-descended former dictator of Peru."
      ],
      "answer": "Alberto Fujimori"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. During this campaign, George A. Dodd led the so-called “last true cavalry charge.” An officer in this campaign strapped two captured soldiers on the hood of his car and carved three notches in his pistols. Four “flying columns” were dispatched during this campaign, which saw fighting at the town of (20 pts)",
        "Parral and the use of Buffalo Soldiers at Guerrero. A´lvaro Obreg´on threatened to attack this (10 pts)",
        "expedition, which began after the Division of the North attacked Columbus, New Mexico. For ten points, name this 1916-17 expedition led by John Pershing, a failed attempt to capture a Mexican soldier."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Punitive Expedition",
        "descriptions of John “Blackjack” Pershing’s expedition to capture Pancho Villa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the early 20th century, this state contracted some of its prison population to its northern neighbor until Commissioner of Charities and Corrections Kate Barnard investigated. A racist governor of this state, William Murray, boasted to farmers so much he earned the nickname “Alfalfa Bill.” A (20 pts)",
        "riot in this state began after Sarah Page was allegedly attacked by Dick Rowland in an elevator and resulted in a white mob setting fire to (10 pts)",
        "“Black Wall Street.” In 1889, the Indian Appropriations Act led to a land rush in, for ten points, what state where Greenwood race riot took place in Tulsa, decades after the “Boomers” and “Sooners” rushed in?"
      ],
      "answer": "Oklahoma"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader’s navy was damaged when John Vassall was blackmailed into being a Soviet spy. Though this politician began the Polaris nuclear project, he ended the National Service and joined the USSR and United States as the third major country to sign the Partial Test Ban Treaty. This man’s (20 pts)",
        "cabinet was rocked by the revelation that Christine Keeler had an affair with the Secretary of State for War, John Profumo. This Prime Minister’s (10 pts)",
        "sub-Saharan tour of Africa is credited with speeding up decolonization. For ten points, name this Conservative Prime Minister of the UK who gave the 1960 “Wind of Change” speech in South Africa."
      ],
      "answer": "Harold MacMillan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Escalation in tensions before this war included a bombardment ordered by Lord Napier and a seizure of stockpiles by Charles Elliott. As a result of successful operations in this war, the name “devil ship” was given to the iron warship (20 pts)",
        "Nemesis. During this war, Chusan and the Bogue Forts on the Pearl River Delta were captured. To end this war, the (10 pts)",
        "Daoguang Emperor accepted the Treaty of Nanking, granting Hong Kong to Britain. For ten points, name this 1839-42 war in China sparked by the trade of addictive narcotics."
      ],
      "answer": "First Opium War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Prior to this event, its perpetrator admitted that he was “going to strike a strong blow. Things are going to get hot,” and, in a meeting with Jean Drepeau, noted, “I have to speak to those people who are calling for me.” In the wake of this event, (20 pts)",
        "Pierre Trudeau was labeled “the enemy of the ‘French fact’”. This incident, which took place during Expo 67, took place on a balcony at (10 pts)",
        "Montreal City Hall. Lester Pearson issued the retort “The people of Canada are free” after, for ten points, what July 1967 international incident in which Charles de Gaulle stoked Qu´eb´ecois nationalism with a controversial four-word phrase?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Charles de Gaulle proclaiming Vive le Qu´ebec libre! or Long live free Qu´ebec!",
        "prompt on descriptions of de Gaulle visiting Montreal, Canada"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After Lord Dufferin offered to create a “free state” in this province, many Icelandic Mormons traveled to its colony of New Iceland. Due to incorrect metric conversions, an Air Canada flight had to land in this province’s town of (20 pts)",
        "Gimli. Thomas Greenway and Wilfrid Laurier defused a 19th century crisis over religion and language in this province’s schools. Premier Duff Roblin had to build a floodway in this province after the (10 pts)",
        "Red River of the North overflowed. For ten points, name this Canadian province where, in 1919, a general strike disrupted Winnipeg."
      ],
      "answer": "Manitoba"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was saved from being burnt alive by Mohawk Indians after rain and a French officer intervened. As a member of the Sons of Liberty, he threatened to level Connecticut Governor Thomas Fitch’s home if Stamp Tax paper was not given up. Under George Washington, this man was forced to retreat from the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Long Island, and he faced court martial after losing Forts Clinton and Montgomery. As a major general in the Continental Army, this man may have told William (10 pts)",
        "Prescott to give the order, “Don’t fire until you see the whites of their eyes.” For ten points, name this general who fought at the Battle of Bunker Hill."
      ],
      "answer": "Israel Putnam"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "A portion of one of these structures was built in Kicking Horse Pass on the border of Alberta and British Columbia. Construction of one of these structures was led by Sandford Fleming, and the Pacific Scandal involved the building of one of these structures. Navvies [[NAH-vees]] and (*) coolies helped build one of these structures for Canada for which Craigellachie [[kruh-GEH-luh-kee]] was the site of the last (*) spike. The Canadian Pacific forms, for ten points, what type of structure which crosses North America?"
      ],
      "answer": "Transcontinental Railroad"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader's government outlined seven \"dangerous Western values\" in \"Document Number 9.\" This leader's namesake form of Socialist thought is presented as a continuation of the \"Three Represents\" and Scientific Development Perspective. This leader abolished (20 pts)",
        "term limits, effectively allowing him to rule indefinitely. This leader sought to extend his country's influence in Africa and South-Central Asia through infrastructure investment as part of the (10 pts)",
        "Belt and Road Initiative. For ten points, name this General Secretary of the Chinese Communist Party."
      ],
      "answer": "Xi ] Jinping"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This non-Chinese figure trained at the Whampoa Military Academy and offered David Ben-Gurion and the Jewish people a homeland in his nation. This politician used the pseudonym \"Nguyen [[WHEN]] the (20 pts)",
        "Patriot\" while writing articles prior to the Versailles Peace Talks. This man led the 1945 August General Uprising which successfully deposed the colonial French following the nine-year First (10 pts)",
        "Indochina War. The city of Saigon was renamed in honor of, for ten points, which first president of communist Vietnam?"
      ],
      "answer": "Ho Chi Minh or Nguyễn Sinh Cung"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Soe Naing was the first of over a hundred journalists from this nation to be imprisoned in 2021, with many being placed in the Insein Prison first run by the State Law and Order (20 pts)",
        "Restoration Council. 2020 election results in this nation were annulled following a coup by the Tatmadaw [[taht-MAH-\"tau\"]] armed forces. That coup removed Aung (10 pts)",
        "San Suu Kyi [[CHEE]] from power in, for ten points, which southeast Asian nation, once known as Burma?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Myanmar",
        "Republic of the Union of Myanmar",
        "or Pyidaunzu Thanmăda Myăma Nainngandaw",
        "Burma before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A Venetian convert led a subset of these states and built his namesake mosque to impress Lalla Lalla Oum, a princess of the Kabyle [[KAH-beel]]. Ships of this polity departing from Sale [[SAH-leh]] (20 pts)",
        "traveled across the Atlantic during a 17th century raid on Iceland in search of slaves. With assistance from Sweden and Sicily, the U.S. fought two namesake (10 pts)",
        "wars with people of these states, culminating in a blockade of Tripoli. For ten points, name these historical “pirate states” of the North African coast."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Barbary States",
        "Barbary Coast",
        "or Berber Coast"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One way to circumvent this general project is Psiphon [[\"SIGH\"-fohn]], created by the Computer Science department of the University of Toronto. One part of this series of laws is the Golden Shield Project, a (20 pts)",
        "mass-surveillance and censoring system, supervised by the Public Security Bureau. This collection of legislation aims to prevent citizens from researching things like the Falun Gong or (10 pts)",
        "Xinjiang internment camps. For ten points, give this collective name for a series of legislation enforced by the People’s Republic of China to regulate the domestic Internet."
      ],
      "answer": "Great Firewall or Fánghuǒ Chángchéng"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The salutation of the sun by Syrian soldiers under this general was misinterpreted by the enemy army led by Vitellian as incoming reinforcements, causing them to break at the Second Battle of Bedriacum. The supposed descendant of Julius Caesar, Gaius Julius Civilis, rose in rebellion against this leader during the (20 pts)",
        "Batavian Rebellion. This emperor, who deployed the general Agricola to Britain, also ordered the construction of the (10 pts)",
        "Coliseum. The victor of the Year of Four Emperors was, for ten points, which Roman Emperor and founder of the Flavian dynasty?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Vespasian or Vespasianus",
        "Titus Flavius Vespasianus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader personally led troops into Dai Viet after its Trần Dynasty was usurped by the popular general, Hồ Quý Ly [[HO KWEE LEE]]. This man overthrew his pacifist brother, the Jianwen Emperor, and ordered the construction of the (20 pts)",
        "Porcelain Tower and had the Grand Canal repaired. This emperor funded the \"Treasure Fleets\" of Muslim eunuch and Chinese admiral (10 pts)",
        "Zheng He [[ZHEHNG HUH]], who extorted tribute from various Indian Ocean states. For ten points, name this Ming Emperor who moved the imperial capital to Beijing."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Yongle Emperor",
        "Zhu Di"
      ]
    }
  ]
}